Hello and welcome back to
another video with it's Dr.
Dan.
And we're gonna continue looking
at math skills to ACE chemistry.
And today we're gonna be looking at
unit conversions, which is arguably
the most important math skill that
you need to pass chemistry in general.
And that's not to scare you, but that's
being that it is a part of our labs.
It's a part of almost every single
chapter that you'll come across in chem.
So when it comes to studying this, you
really want to make sure you take the time
and practice as many problems as possible.
But let's talk about exactly
what this has entail.
So with this, the first thing is
there's a couple key little definitions.
One is dimensional analysis, which is a
term that gets thrown around quite often
within your first few weeks of chemistry.
What this is is a mathematical method
used to convert measured units, and
it's that keyword measured, which
keeps getting brought up, right?
You're in a lab, you're taking
measurements, masses, volumes,
length, time, temperature.
You will be converting them
to a different, to different
things that will help illustrate
the meaning of your reactions.
So, you need these to answer problems.
So you're gonna continuously
see that from time again.
So, when you're doing unit
conversions, the key thing is, is
that it you're going to be using
conversion factors, which are ratios
or relationships between defined units.
So, one really easy example of that
is if you think of a foot, right?
And I ask you, how many
inches are in a foot?
Well, for all my American
people out there, right?
You can think 12 inches is one foot.
Or if I ask you, How many
centimeters is in one meter?
Well, 100 centimeters is one meter.
Those are defined terms.
Or if you ask how many pennies
are in a dollar, right?
100 pennies are in $1.
Another conversion term.
Let, let's look that.
So the basic ideas of just using our
algebra, so what you learned a really
long time ago, maybe in grade school or
high school, starting with fractions.
So how do fractions work?
Well, if I kind of set up the following
problem, and let's say I want to know.
If I have two over seven and I times that
by three over two, well, you can do your
cal, you can rip out a calculator and you
could calculate this and easily solve it.
However, we can simplify this
problem by just doing some little
cancellation when it came to fractions.
When you have the same units.
Same units, or.
Numbers, they cancel when
they're opposite of each other.
So in this particular example, you can see
that the twos are opposite and they are
the same, so they can cancel and simplify.
So, each two will cancel
and simplify down to one.
So, if I do the math here where I
multiply across, We can see that we
have one times three, and then on
the bottom we have seven times one,
so we can get our simplified answer.
So, when you are doing units,
it's gonna be a similar idea.
I.
So let's look at this in
an analogy for ourselves.
What exactly does unit conversion mean?
So if I have the following little
picture, let's say I have three
little creatures here and they
all speak different languages.
So if I have the first one and he only
speaks Spanish, so he speaks Spanish,
however, He wants to speak to the bird,
which the bird only speaks French, so
how can they communicate to each other?
Well, if you kind of think in our everyday
lives, if we have someone who cannot speak
the same language, well, what do you do?
You have a translator.
You have someone that can interpret that.
So we find another bunny in the middle
with a little thumbs up, and we find
out that, oh, they speak French.
And they also speak Spanish as well.
So what are they gonna do?
They're gonna help translate
that conversation between
all these little creatures.
So when we have that, we can set
this up like a fraction problem.
So how would you do that?
Well, if I have my first funny that
is Spanish and I multiply that by my
second one, which is a fraction, right?
So we have Spanish, which is our given.
French, which is our desired.
One thing you'll notice is that
Spanish cancels out Spanish and
that only equals French, so it
is also a mathematical problem.
Now, the thing about that is
there's an easier way to show
this rather than just fractions.
We're gonna be using something
called Tea Tables, which help us
illustrate these types of problems.
So when we do this, we'll set up a
little table like this, where every
single one, where we have a line
across, which represents our problems.
So if I have the first one, which was
Spanish, I would insert my little parts
of the problem, so French, Spanish.
And then we can see that, oh, this cancels
our units, giving us our one little piece.
So we're gonna go through unit
conversions and do several
problems and examples through this.
So why don't we check it out as
we go forward of how we can use
unit conversions in chemistry.
I.
Okay, so with this next one, so
suppose a model car measures to be 15
centimeters long, how many inches is that?
So you can try to Google that, right?
You can see how many centimeters are an
inch, but how do you set up a problem?
How do you go through it?
So when you have problems like these,
the first thing you're going to do is
you're going to highlight and determine
all the important piece of information.
So we see that we have a 15 centimeter
object and we want to know how
many inches is this going to be.
So when we do this, we write down what
our given pieces of information are,
which we can see, okay, well we are given,
we have 15 centimeters is one thing.
And we desire it to be in inches, right?
We are in the US so we want it to be in
the US system, but we need to be able
to communicate effectively with metric
system because it is a global system.
So how do you go about that?
So we need to define what
that, that,  conversion is to
go from one unit to another.
So when you are doing these types of
things, most likely you will have a
conversion sheet available to you.
If you do well, we can look up how
many centimeters there are in an
inch, and when you do, you'll see that
there's 2.54 centimeters in one inch.
And if you wanna take that time, you
can pause the video and try to find
that, or just going off my word.
So when you have that relationship,
right, that they are equivalent
to one another, we can illustrate
that as that they're equal.
But they are also represented
of ratios or fractions.
So when we do that, we can say, okay, 2.54
centimeters is equivalent to one inch.
Or we can write it as the reverse or
the flipped version of that where one
inch is equivalent to 2.54 centimeters.
Now when we do these problems,
I'm gonna color code these.
We have to let the units
guide our thinking.
So let units guide you, meaning that we
have to let them show us how we are going
to be canceling these different problems.
So going back to our
translator problem, right?
When it came to Spanish and
Spanish, they were opposite.
So they canceled in this case, right?
We have centimeters on top.
Those centimeters needs
to cancel here as well.
If we look at our two, where we have
purple and yellow, well the yellow one
has it where centimeters is on bottom, so
we can see that oh, centimeters, cancel
centimeters, they're both gonna cancel,
leaving us with only inches as a result.
So that's our final unit, so we
can go through and calculate that.
So when we do the math for that,
we can see 15 divided by 2.54.
And we will get that.
We will have 5.9 centimeters
as our final answer.
Or, sorry, not 5.9 centimeters.
5.9 inches as our final answer.
Okay?
We'll box that off, and that's how
you go through a basic conversion.
Let's look further into this.
So let's try to understand how
these conversions come about.
So when you are understanding
conversions in lab, It's all based on the
international system of units or SI units.
You'll commonly hear your
professor mention that word.
This is the preferred
method of measurement.
The reason for that is because it's
not just for chemistry, but it's for
your entire scientific community.
And for many of you that watch
this channel, you're interested
in the global health community.
So whether you wanna be a nurse or
maybe a dental hygienist or a some
sort of caregiver, We commonly are
talking in the metric system because
it is applicable to the entire world.
So what we are looking at is
most of these measurements
refer directly to a base unit.
So that is our measurement.
There's some types of base units
that you'll see very commonly
are like for length or meters
mass are kilograms, right?
So where you used to maybe more
like pounds, but kilograms is
an easier unit to work with.
Volumes.
So liters, kelvin is temperature
seconds, time, or moles.
And future videos we'll
see a lot of moles.
Um, we deal with a lot of these and
these are our different base units.
Now these are the standard for
what we, how we look at them.
Now, all these individual base
units can be edited with a prefix.
So being that all the base units,
they operate on a 10 base scale.
So meaning in order to simplify the
mathematics, we can put a prefix in front
of it to make it a smaller or a larger
number to make it easier to handle.
So that way we're not always
dealing with these ridiculously
sized numbers all the time.
It depends on, what are you talking about?
Are we referring to
chemistry, bio, physics?
Every one of them has their own scale.
So, when it comes to prefixes, they have
a base unit multiplier, meaning let's say
if I have liter, for example, I could say
that I have 10 to the nine liters, which
is equivalent to one gigaliter, which
would be the first prefix on this list.
Now mean there are so many mnemonics
and we'll refer back to this, we'll
refer back to the list over here, right?
We, you should, and try to remember these.
I would recommend heavily to put
these on flashcards for yourself.
Being that you will probably
need them at some point.
So when you are trying to learn and,
figure all these out,  there is a
simple mnemonic for it, which is for.
To try to remember all these.
So I'll read the prefixes first.
So when you are starting these,
we start from the top, which is
giga-, mega- kilo-, Heto- deca-.
Then your base unit, Deci-
Centi-, Milli-, micro-, and nano-.
Now there is a prefix, a little
mnemonic, so if you remember the great
Mighty King Henry died by drinking
chocolate or chunky milk Monday night.
You can kind of remember
a little image with that.
It'll help you remember all your prefixes.
So mnemonics are very, very
helpful when it comes to these.
So, If you remember that the great
Mighty King Henry died drinking
chunky milk on Monday night, it will
help you remember your prefixes.
Now, the values for that, that will
come with practice, the more you
practice it, the easier it will get.
So let's work on trying to define those.
How can we write them as a unit
conversion like we practiced before?
So let's do some, some normal ones.
If I asked you, all right, well, if I have
one liter, how many milliliters are there?
Okay, so what we could do is we would
look up our Millie prefix and we'd
look across and we can see, all right,
well, the base unit multiplier is one
that's referring directly to liters.
So as we are showing here, right,
we have one leader and let's,
use a bigger font size here.
So if I have one leader, That's gonna be
equivalent to 1000 milliliters, and we can
see that 10 to the three, the three power.
So 10 to the three is referring
to the three zeros that are here.
So just as a reminder, we can
show this in many different ways.
We can define it as a fraction, right?
We can say 1000 milliliters is one liter.
Or we can flip it and say one
liter is 1000 milliliters.
We can do others.
If I have, let's say one of the larger
ones, let's say if we do,  kilo-.
So up here you can notice that
the base multiplier now all
of a sudden has a value to it.
So the base unit
multiplier is 10 to three.
So if I asked you how many grams are
there in a kilogram, we could do that.
So if I have one kilogram.
We could see that on the right
hand side, right here, right?
One kilogram.
And that's gonna be equal
to 10 to three grams.
That's 1000 grams.
And we can go through and
define that ratio as well.
So if I wanted to, I could write,
all right, 1000 grams is equal
to one kilogram, or one kilogram
is equal to a thousand grams.
The way to really look at this table
is everything on the top is big.
Everything on the bottom is tiny, and
that's in respect to the base unit.
So the base unit is really small
on the top, and it's really,
really big on the bottom.
So that's kind of the idea here
is how many of them does it
required to make that thing now?
Let's try to do some examples of that
and try to practice it for ourselves.
So if I have the first one here, it
says, convert 22.4 liters to milliliters.
So what you would have to
do is go to your tables.
Now we define this one before.
Uh, so we said that one liter
is equal to 1000 milliliters.
So let's do this problem.
Let's go through our steps.
First thing you're going to do
is write down what is given.
First thing we have is we have 22.4
liters, and we also have the conversion
term from before, which was one liter
is a thousand mL's, or one liter is
a thousand mL's on the flip side.
Right?
And what we desire is
that we want to find mL's.
Okay, so let's set this up.
As a table for ourselves.
So what we're gonna do is we're
gonna write our little line and
we're going to show our T table.
We will start with the 22.4 liters.
And what we have to do is you remember the
tip from before, let the units guide you.
So if we let things guide
you, how do we cancel leaders?
Which one can I use?
Do I use the one on the left
or the one on the right when
it comes to these conversions?
And the thing you will see is that,
well, if I use the one on the right
here, well leaders will cancel leaders
because they are opposite of each other.
Right?
They are opposite.
So, and that's the big idea.
If they are opposite, they will cancel.
So we have the 1000 mL's on top,
one liter on the bottom, and
then we can show, okay, leaders
cancels leaders, they both go away.
And it leaves us only with milliliters.
So when we do this problem, we
will see that we will get an
answer of 22,400 milliliters.
If you want some practice with scientific
notation, it's a good time to do it.
'cause we should be practicing all of
our skills so we can see, alright, if
I wanna put this scientific notation, I
gotta move that decimal place four times.
It's gonna be 2.24 times 10
to the fourth milliliters.
Both answers will be correct in this case.
It just depends on really what's more
convenient for you and your situation.
Let's do another, so for this next one,
if you want to convert 3.4 milligrams
to kilograms, how can you do that?
Well, First what we're gonna do
is we write down our given, right,
we have that 3.4 milligrams.
We desire to go to kilograms, so
what we need to do is write down all
conversion terms that are relevant.
Now, I picked this one on purpose because
there is a bigger prefix gap here.
Let's slide up to the prefixes
for this particular problem.
We are going from mil, milli- to kilo-
just like earlier, meaning that there
is a large gap between these two areas
that we can see whenever there is
a gap, whether it's from one prefix
to a lower one or to a higher one.
Good strategy is split
it up into two steps.
And why would you do that?
It's because all of these modifiers
that we see, Are all in respect to the
base unit that I have here in yellow.
So meaning the first do one
conversion to the base unit and
then do a second conversion out
to the number that you desire.
So let's write them both down and
I'll show you in this example.
So we're gonna write it down
for Millie and for and from, uh,
and from the base unit to Kilo.
But let's do that.
So what we have, Is we have
1000 milligrams is one gram.
We'll write that down.
And then we also have that
1000 grams is one milligram.
So from our choices, what we
are going to do is determine how
to, how to start this problem.
'cause we have.
Four different puzzle pieces
that we can choose from, right?
We have this one, I'll try
to use different colors.
We have this one, we have
purple, yellow, red, and blue.
Oh, that is not blue and blue.
So we have all these choices.
So if I start with my first part, which
is my milligrams, and I'll put that in
my table, how would I cancel my unit?
So let the units guide you.
So first cancel milligrams.
So we need milligrams to be
opposite of our milligrams.
So looking at my pieces, we
can see the yellow one above
is the one that fits the best.
So let's put that here.
Right?
You can see MG is opposite of mg.
Fees cancel, and then our units
are now grams as a result.
Now are we finished our problem?
And the answer is no.
Right?
We want to get the kilograms.
So how do we let the units guide us?
Well, grams now need to get canceled, so
when we kind of do that right, grams need
to be opposite of grams and we can just,
can now see that Well, okay, the purple
piece now cancels are are shiny purple.
Uh, the blue piece cancels are
units for grams, two kilograms.
Right.
So 1000 grams is one kilogram,
which as a result, and you can check
yourself, is that this leaves us
with the units that we desire, right?
We want kilograms to put a
little check next to it, to
double, double check yourself.
'cause you can see that even
I made a small mistake there,
which is really normal, right?
It's easy to get a little mixed up.
So when we do this problem, you multiply
everything on top, divide all the things
on the bottom, or if you want, you can
also remember that each one of these
little line sections here, so this
part or here, these are all fractions.
So you can always set them up in your
calculate, like a fraction as well.
So if I do this right, I have
3.4 times one times one divided
by 1000, divided by 1000.
So when we do that, our final answer,
it's gonna be a very tiny number.
So I'm gonna put in
scientific notation first.
And this is in kilograms, so
it's 3.4 times 10 in negative
six kilograms, or 0.0 0 0, 0 0.
Um, three, four kilograms.
So it's a very small
number that you can choose.
For your answer.
Personally, I am a bigger fan of
scientific notation, but if you're
new to chem, usually everybody goes
for the other option for a little
while until you're comfortable.
All right, so now for our very last note
before we sign off for this video on unit
conversions, you'll also have to do unit
conversions for us to metric as well.
The only big difference about this
versus with SI units is that US units
and metrics, they are their own systems.
So meaning that if you have to do a US to
metric conversion, these are all measured.
So meaning that we have a specific
measurement for each of these, and
they all came up with their own
unique method of how they came about.
So when you use them, you have
to consider significant figures.
In the calculation.
So with most of these conversions before,
the number that you were given at the
very beginning was how many sig figs
you needed at the end of the problem.
However, if you use a US conversion,
you can kind of see in these that
all of these values, they have the
measured terms in it, which actually
have the decimal points in them.
They can affect your calculation.
So if you choose to use one, use
one with more decimal places or
significant digits, so that way it does
not affect your rounding in the end.
So use one with more values.
So keep that in mind when you
are doing future calculations.
Um, as you are going through these,
I hope that this video helped you.
There will be a new V, there will be
two new videos coming out very soon.
One will be a follow up to this one in
terms of some extra practice problems
for this, which are harder problems.
So there'll be going through
us to metric conversions.
So do an example of that, doing
cubed volumes, so using things
that are like CMD cubed, and then
doing a multi-step unit conversion.
The other video, which should come
out within the next few days is on
dimensional analysis, and by the time
some people watch this and be already
out for a long time, but dimensional
analysis more specifically on word
problems and how to decipher them.
So please stay tuned for those videos.
Please like and subscribe and
tell me what you think about them.
Tell me if there's anything you
would love a video on to help
you pass your chemistry class.
I will try to make that as soon as I can.
All right.
Thank you so much.
This has been Dr.
Dan and I will see you all
soon and see you next time.
Bye now.